<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Humble address offer'd to the consideration of the Lords and Commons touching a law concerning perjury</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44965</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3387</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5782</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12086406</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12086406</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53758</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44965)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53758)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 73:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Humble address offer'd to the consideration of the Lords and Commons touching a law concerning perjury</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Perjury --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="address">
            <pb facs="tcp:53758:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN HUMBLE ADDRESS Offer'd to the CONSIDERATION OF THE <hi>Lords and Commons</hi> Touching a Law concerning Perjury.</head>
            <p>WHEN contagious Diſeaſes reign, its natural for Men to have recourſe to, and make their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to Phyſicians, for their Direction and Help, as Perſons, who by their Profeſſion, are preſumed to be the moſt knowing in ſuch an Affair, and in the compaſs of whoſe Art it may probably lie to preſcribe Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, that may quell and totally ſubdue their power, at leaſt ſo control it, that they may not licentiouſly domineer and rage, to the utter depopulating of their Dwelling-places.</p>
            <p>And thus when ſome heinous Immorality predominates in a Nation above any other, and good Men are under juſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and fears leaſt the Diſtemper grow Epidemical, it's rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable for them to reſort to the Civil Governments, and requeſt of them the making of ſome Antidote, the framing of ſome wholſome Law againſt it, which may either kill it out-right, entirely ſuppreſs, or correct its Poyſon ſo, that it may not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it ſelf over the ſeveral parts of the Body Politic, to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the whole.</p>
            <p>Such an Immorality is Perjury, eſpecially when it is ſolemn, and committed before a Judicatory; the prodigious increaſe whereof in this Kingdom theſe late Years, more particularly from 1678, until this preſent time, eaſily obſervable by the moſt unthinking and incurious, and yet never enough to be deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by any who believe the Exiſtence of a Deity, that a Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb facs="tcp:53758:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
is due to his great Name, or have a ſenſe, that the Honor of his Majeſty is deeply wounded by this Sin, is the ſole occaſion of this Addreſs to you, my Lords and Gentlemen, as thoſe in whoſe power it lies, by the making proviſion of ſome ſeverer Remedy, than is yet to be found extant among our Laws, for the giving a check to its daily growth, obſtructing its farther Progreſs, and wider ſpreading it ſelf among us, to be ſerviceable to God's Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and beneficial to your Country; it being Penn'd to implore your immediate Aſſiſtance in preparing ſuch a Bill as your Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſhall think moſt expedient to this end, and to uſe your ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavor afterwards, that it may have the force of a Law.</p>
            <p>And while I offer ſuch an humble <hi>Addreſs</hi> to you, for the beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging your aid, and that you would be pleas'd to ſet your hands to this excellent Work with all the ſpeed you can, I have judg'd with my ſelf it may not be uſeleſs to premiſe ſomething by way of Advance concerning the horrid Guilt of cuſtomary Swearing, to make this of ſolemn Forſwearing to have, as indeed it hath, a far more horrid Aſpect, and ſo by this means, excite in you the greater Deteſtation of that Wickedneſs for its hideous Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſneſs, and a ſprightlier Zeal to curb it.</p>
            <p>For though I am ſufficiently perſwaded there are very many Knowing Perſons in your Illuſtrious Aſſembly, whoſe Abilities can more exactly repreſent to themſelves this Villany in all its Blackneſs and Deformity than my Weakneſs can, yet, I preſume, I may without juſtly and deſervedly incurring the Imputation of doing an unneceſſary and ſuperfluous work, be allow'd in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Example, writing to thoſe who were before ſufficiently inform'd in the Chriſtian Doctrine, to put you all <note place="margin">Pet. 2. c. 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 12.</note> in remembrance of what you know already.</p>
            <p>But beſides, being only your Monitor and not your Inſtructer in this Point, I conſider, that having your Thoughts employ'd by multiplicity of Buſineſs, and Public Affairs lying before you, you want that leiſure to make thoſe Reflections on the Flagiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of this Crime, which your Minds not otherwiſe occupied could themſelves Suggeſt, and yet withal as buſied as you are, you may find a Vacancy to peruſe ſuch, which are made fit for your hands by another.</p>
            <p>And where for want of leiſure to recollect what you know on this Subject, you may not form ſo full an Idea of its Uglineſs, nor conſequently entertain ſuch a perfect Abhorrence of it, as may ſtir up and quicken you to ſet about framing ſuch a Bill, as is convenient for the fore mention'd purpoſe, and expediting it with all the ſpeed poſſible; yet what is more negligently and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53758:2"/>
looſly ſaid or thought on ſuch a matter by another, than would have been by your ſelves, could you ſpare time to take a view of it in your own Minds may in ſome meaſure ſerve to ſupply this, and warm you with ſuch a degree of hatred againſt it, as may engage you to ſet about drawing ſuch a Bill, and diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in ſome reaſonable and convenient time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. If then Laws ſhould be enacted againſt Common Swearing, or thoſe already paſt for corroborating the Divine Prohibition of this Sin, with civil Sanctions and temporal Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, be put in full Execution, or you ſupplicated to ſee this done, becauſe it's a diſreſpectful uſing the Name of God, and ſo a ſlight put upon him, whoſe Majeſty ſignified by it, is in all Relations to be infinitely revered by us, <hi>i. e.</hi> as far as we are able, commenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably to it ſelf, and the being over familiar with his Name in our Mouths without conſidering the Reaſons, the occaſions we have to uſe it, the end for which, and the manner how, is an act of the higheſt Malapertneſs and Sawcineſs, and withal, this ſhould be done out of a juſt Caution leaſt a cuſtomary uſing the Name of the moſt High lightly, and without any regard at all, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which are as they aſſever, bring Men on a ſudden to apply that dreadful Name to things that are utterly falſe; an abſtinence from ſwearing at all being the ſureſt mound and fence againſt <note place="margin">Cic pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Roſcie.</note> Perjury: (For if the Obſervation of one of the greateſt and wiſeſt Perſons, who ere wore the <hi>Roman</hi> Gown) hold good, as no doubt it doth, that an habitual Lyar is very apt to be perjur'd, it is moſt certain that a frequent Swearer is in nearer danger of forſwearing himſelf than ſuch a one; Attention to what he depoſeth being only able to preſerve ſuch a one from committing Perjury, which he wants who Swears raſhly and precipitately, and by an invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Cuſtom of Swearing, is very oft inſenſible whether he Swears or not.</p>
            <p>If for theſe Reaſons, I ſay, common Swearing ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd by your deviſing of new Laws, or by your iſſuing out your Orders for the Execution of the good ones we already have; and theſe are Motives cogent enough to Petition you, that you would ſee this effectually done, the Reaſons are more urgent and preſſing, and the Motives more violent, why you ſhould be apply'd unto, for the framing ſome ſharp Act to prevent Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in Courts of Juſtice more eminently, or to correct it, ſince that the Nation is already furniſht with, is in the nature of its Conſtitution too feeble to effect it, the Puniſhment to be inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on an Offender of this kind, being only the forfeiture of 20 <hi>l.</hi> and ſix Months Impriſonment, if he hath a Purſe to pay, and ſtanding only in the Pillory with his Ears nail'd to it if he be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvent;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53758:3"/>
and that of the Suborner to this Wickedneſs being only a Fine of 40 <hi>l.</hi> and 6 Months Impriſonment, and ſtanding <note place="margin">5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 9.</note> an Hour on the Pillory, and a diſabling both to give Evidence for the future, till the Judgment be revers'd by Attaint, or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>And yet the Crime of Perjury is of that outrageous Nature, that it's an affronting God in the higheſt degree, and moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking manner that Men are capable of doing it, it's a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting and Suborning as much as in them lies, or thinking they may be able to do ſo, Him who is Eternal Truth, Truth it ſelf, to be a witneſs to a Lye; it's a deriſion of his Omniſcience, a ſcorning his Juſtice, and bidding defiance to his Almighty Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, while they call him in to be a Witneſs to what they ſay, and a judge of their Falſhood, if guilty of any, imprecating him in this caſe to avenge it, with pouring out his Judgments upon their heads, which they would not be ſo preſumptuous and daring to do, if they did believe any thing of his taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of this, of his Inclinations and Will, or his being in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to puniſh their Perfidiouſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. And as the Crime is of a more enormous bulk, and more affrightful Complexion than any other, except it be a flat and obſtinate denial of his Exiſtence, or transferring that Honour and Worſhip, which is his peculiar prerogative to his Workmanſhip, or rather the immediate Workmanſhip of Mens hands, yea in ſome ſort equals their Magnitude, and is of the ſame dark hue with them if it doth not exceed them, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it is a mocking him, which our Eſtimation placeth in the foremoſt rank of Injuries, that can be done us; ſo in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion it draws a Judgment upon the Perſon greater than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; God having poſitively declared that he will not hold a Criminal of this kind Guiltleſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> that he will not pardon <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.</note> him, threatned that he himſelf will be a ſwift Witneſs againſt ſuch a one, perſue him to Condemnation, and pronounced far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.5.</note> that the flying Roll or Sithe in the Tranſlation of the 70, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 53.</note> 20 Cubits long, and 10 broad, ſhall enter into his Houſe, and conſume the Stones with the Timber thereof, <hi>i. e.</hi> lay his Family and Eſtate waſt, and the Heathen Oracle mention'd by <hi>Herodotus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> threatned as much.</p>
            <p>And its no wonder ſo dreadful a Puniſhment from God pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues it, ſince it's a Complication of other Sins, not meerly a contumely againſt him, but a wrong to our Neighbor, generally fails not to be join'd with Theft and Murther, taking away the Lives, and ſweeping away the Eſtates of the Innocent, and ſo is not barely an omiſſion of that common duty of Juſtice we owe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53758:3"/>
us (which certainly is to have our Lives and Eſtates and Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations defended and ſecured,) but a direct Commiſſion againſt the Rule of it, in doing that to others, which we would not have done to our ſelves, deſpoiling them of their good Name, Honors, Poſſeſſions, and their very being, to make it a compleat and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate Villany.</p>
            <p>It not only changes the courſe of Juſtice, which ſhould be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually adminiſter'd to all, every man that is born into the World, having a natural claim to have right done him, but perverts it; not only damns up thoſe ſtreams, which ſhould ſo flow, as every one ſhould be refreſh'd by them, but turns them into a clean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary channel, where with their Rapidneſs they carry away and overwhelm thoſe, whoſe merits requir'd a far different fate, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſharpning and turning the edge of the Sword or Axe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Delinquents and Malefactors, for whom the Law appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, it makes theſe apply'd to the cutting off the moſt virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and honeſt in a Public Society, as it did moſt eminently at <hi>Athens</hi> while the 30 tyranniz'd there, or at <hi>Rome</hi> under the alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natively prevailing Factions of <hi>Marius</hi> and <hi>Sylla,</hi> all whoſe ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born and incorruptible Integrity will not ſuffer them to bow down to Uſurpation, or applaud and congratulate Violences.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> But Vengeance doth not only purſue, and at laſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, and ſeverely ſcurge perjur'd Perſons themſelves and their Poſterity, whom it oft roots out from the face of the Earth; but likewiſe this crime, if ſuffer'd to eſcape ſcot free by Civil Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories, which ſhould puniſh it, doth many times over and above drawd own from Heaven heavy and ſore Judgments upon a whole Nation, where it is thus ſuffer'd to go off with Impunity, or march off in triumph over defeated Juſtice.</p>
            <p>This Sin is uſually ſpecified by the Prophets, <hi>Jeremiah</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as one of thoſe many crying ones, which inſtigated God to threaten the <hi>Jews</hi> with Extirpation out of their own, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation into a foreign Land, and incens'd him afterwards to put that Sentence in Execution, becauſe, though they ſwore as the Lord liveth, yet they ſwore falſly.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> Howbeit ſhould no Calamity overtake a Nation, where this Sin is rife, and no Judicial Cogniſance taken of it, or diſmiſs'd in Courts with a ſhrug or grimace only, yet it's a foul diſgrace to that People, where it's frequently practiſed and rarely diſcountenanced; Sin, It was the wiſe Man's Obſervation long ago, is a reproach to any People of what kind ſoever it be, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.</note> as Drunkenneſs, Gluttony, Wantonneſs, Inconſtancy wherewith ſome Nations are tax'd as their Epidemical Diſeaſes by others,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53758:4"/>
which are ſound and free from them. But none caſts a blacker and yet juſter Aſperſion upon a People than Perfidiouſneſs.</p>
            <p>The uſe of an Oath is a tacit Reproach thrown upon Mankind by themſelves, for their baſeneſs; for it implies they cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve one the other upon their bare words and aſſeverations but that muſt be interpoſed to gain credit to theſe, like as the uſe of Paper or Parchment, Wax; Seals, Subſignations in Contracts and Obligations is a kind of exhibiting a Charge, and giving in Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence againſt their own Honeſty, which they mutually miſtruſt, unleſs guarded with theſe Formalities. But when once words backt with Oaths, Oaths firſt brought into uſe to put doubtful Truth out of queſtion, are not of ſufficient validity to confirm it, nor power enough to gain credit, its the outmoſt Ignominy and Scandal of a Nation.</p>
            <p>What a tainted Reputation have the <hi>Cretians</hi> in Story, when Poets, whoſe buſineſs is Fiction, nay one of their own, who <note place="margin">Epimeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timachus.</note> may be thought would have conceal'd his Country's Shame had it not been too notorious, ſhall charge them with being perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Lyars, and to play the <hi>Cretian</hi> ſhall paſs into a by-word, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting as much as to deceive?</p>
            <p>What a diſcredit is it to the <hi>Greeks</hi> for daring to lard their Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical <note place="margin">Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nal.</note> Relations with Fables? But what a fowler blot is it for for them, the <hi>Ligurians</hi> and <hi>Carthaginians</hi> to be noted for not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving their Faith, and to be tranſmitted to all after Ages with ſuch a Character from the <hi>Roman</hi> Writers, that their faith and downright Perfidiouſneſs, how widely different ſoever theſe two words are in their original Signification, paſs among them, as pieces of the ſame weight and value?</p>
            <p>And albeit ſome one Man of Honor and Principles may make an Exception to a general Character, and by his ſtiffneſs and conſtancy to his Word and Oath may ſerve to redeem his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try from ſuch an Imputation, yet he will hardly have the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to own his deſcent thence without a bluſh, when it is thus ſtigmatized.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 5. But however the worth and honeſty of ſuch a one may help to reſcue his Country's Fame, as the Juſtice of <hi>Ariſtides</hi> may give <hi>Athens</hi> a Credit, whereby ſhe may rival the Glory of <hi>Rome</hi> for her <hi>Cato Cenſorius,</hi> or his great Grandchild of <hi>Utica;</hi> yet the Religion ſuch a Country profeſſeth can never eſcape the having dirt thrown upon it by Men of a different Perſuaſion, if it lets Perjuries, which are as much contrary to the dictates of Natural Religion, as they are againſt the expreſs Prohibitions of Reveal'd and Chriſtian one, go away unpuniſh'd, or what is tantamoun, but lightly. It ſubjects it to extream doubts whether the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53758:4"/>
of ſuch a Denomination, or ſuch a Sect of it be Orthodox or no; however it puts it out of all manner of queſtion that ſuch Profeſſors or Diſciples who are guilty of this outrageous Crime, or wink hard at it, while committed by others, do not believe a ſingle Syllable of its Doctrine to be true, how grave and demure a Countenance ſoever they ſet upon the matter.</p>
            <p>It was eaſy for <hi>Amurath</hi> the II. to imagine Chriſtian Religion gave Countenance to Perjury, when he fully underſtood that <hi>Uladiſlaus</hi> K. of <hi>Hungary</hi> had broken the Truce of 10 Years con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded between them, and confirmed by an Oath, upon the Sollicitation of one of its Purple Fathers, Cardinal <hi>Julian</hi> ſent from its great Patriarch in the Weſt, <hi>Eugene</hi> the IV. to repreſent the Advantages he had to do it, while that Sultan's Arms were employ'd in <hi>Aſia;</hi> and he would have thought he had had an infallible ground to conclude it falſe, had not his Appeal to the God of the Chriſtians, with his hands lifted up to Him in a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bonſin. Dec.</hi> 3. <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Annal. Turcici ad An.</hi> 1443</note> Supplication, (and ſome ſay with the Schedule containing the Articles of Truce held up in them) at the Battle of <hi>Varna,</hi> that he would revenge the Perfidiouſneſs of his followers, been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd with a Victory immediately on his ſide, which before in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to the Chriſtians, <hi>Uladiſlaus</hi> the Breaker of it being ſlain in the Field, and the Cardinal, who inſtigated him to it, in the Perſnit. And ſo it was for <hi>Abimelech</hi> the <hi>Saracen</hi> to think the ſame, had not his appeal againſt the Perjury of <hi>Juſtinian. Rhinotmetus</hi> faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Articles of the broken Peace to a Spear, received the <note place="margin">Cedren.</note> like determination by the diſcomfiture of that Emperors Army.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 6. But, abſtracting from the Religion of an Oath, and the Puniſhment it draws down from God on particular Perſons, or a whole Nation guilty of it, and the Scandal it reflects upon a People, or the Religion profeſs'd by them, the inflicting a light Puniſhment on the Perjur'd, ſuch as makes him no way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd with the fear of undergoing it, creates an opinion in the generality of Mankind, who take their meaſure in judging of the quality of Offences from the penalties allotted to them by the Law, that the Crime is trivial. And ſuch a conceit once imbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by Subjects is apt to ſhake the Crowns on the Heads of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and tends to render all Government precarious and totter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe it is an Invitation to them to break all their Oaths of Obedience to them, the Eſteem of whoſe Religion and Sacred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is a ſtronger ſecurity to them than Guards and Armies.</p>
            <p>Nor can it be reaſonably expected, that they, who have learn'd not to value their Faith ſtak'd down at the Barr in an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertory Oath, ſhould regard the keeping of it pledg'd to them in a Promiſſory one, though ſitting on their Thrones, or in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53758:5"/>
Beſides, as all Government is or ſhould be built upon the baſis of Juſtice; ſo this Virtue muſt be the Pillars and Buttreſſes to ſupport it: And if at any times it happens, as too oft it does, that that Civil Fabrick ſhould be erected upon other Foundations than thoſe of Juſtice, yet upheld it muſt be by doing it. And becauſe it's rarely ſeen that they, who get the Power of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut. v.</hi> 16.</note> into their hands by Fraud and Wrong, are careful of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing right, we may thence prognoſticate, inſtructed by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of paſt Ages, that they will ſoon ſink themſelves and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate into irrevocable Ruine.</p>
            <p>But all adminiſtration of Juſtice muſt of neceſſity be ſtopt, if Perjury be in the way; And in this corrupt and degenerate Eſtate of Mankind, numbers upon the hopes and proſpect of an encouraging Reward, if offer'd, and there no fears of a ſlight Puniſhment, ſhould it be their misfortune to be diſcover'd, will without any difficulty of perſuaſion, be induced and ſtand ready prepar'd to commit it.</p>
            <p>Thus in brief I have laid before you, <hi>My Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> the heinouſneſs of Perjury in its own Nature, and the terrible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it in its Conſequents, to ſpare your pains and time em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd now upon many important Affairs lying before you; ſome portion of which the reducing theſe to your Memories, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering them in your Thoughts would divert; And that taking my riſe thence, I might be the more likely to ſucceed in my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of moving you to prepare ſome Bill for the ſpeedy ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or curbing at leaſt this growing Crime, by providing ſome penalty againſt it, which by its ſharpneſs may be more effectual to the obtaining this end, than that already ordain'd by our Laws.</p>
            <p>Now with all due Submiſſion to your great Prudence and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, <hi>My Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> it's probable that after reſearch and examination, no expedient will be found ſo adequate and appoſite to this purpoſe, no remedy ſo proper for the cure of this Diſtemper as the making this Crime Capital in the Offenders; and fortifying your Bill which ſhall interdict it with the Sanction of Death: For the ſharpneſs of the Law in puniſhing a Crime, diſciplines Men into Virtue and good Life. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sert. Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilius Ap Agellium Noct. At. l.</hi> 20. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Paulus lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Sentent. ad Leg. Cornel. Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamentar. Hi qui cb falſum Teſtimonium perhibendum acceperit, dederint, Judicem ut Sententiam ferat, vel non ferat corruperint, corrumpendumve curaverint, humiliores capite puniantur, honeſtiores publicatis bonis cum ipſo Judice in inſulam deportentur.</hi>
               </note> By the <hi>Roman</hi> Conſtitution, Thoſe, who ſuborned or corrupted any to depoſe falſly againſt another, if their quality was ignoble, were puniſh'd with Death: If their Condition was Honorable with Confiſcation of Goods and Tranſportation, which though a Penalty on this ſide of Death, yet it was in the Eye of their Law a Capital one.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53758:5"/>
Among the <hi>Lycians</hi> a falſe Evidence had his Goods and Eſtate <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heraclid. Ponticus de Lyciis.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Jure Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutio Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitis, v. Zouch. Elem. Jur. P.</hi> 4 §. 9.</note> ſeiz'd on, and was himſelf ſold for a Slave; and the loſs of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty among one of the wiſeſt Nations and beſt able to judge of it, was rank'd with Capital Penalties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at leaſt, I think, the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment with which this Bill ſhould be ſtrengthned ought to bear a juſt proportion and equality with the miſchief intended by the Perjur'd Perſon againſt the Innocent; ſo that whatſoever Puniſhment the Law hath denounc'd againſt an Offence, and the Perſon convicted of it by legal honeſt Witneſſes, was to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, the ſame, if he prov'd his Innocency, ſhould the falſe Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents ſuffer, foraſmuch as their falſe Oaths were directed and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd to do that ſame miſchief to him.</p>
            <p>For that would be but Retaliation, than which no part or act <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>Rabbini in Gomara, Tit. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedr.</hi>
               </note> of Juſtice can be more equal, it being meeting back to Men the ſame meaſure they firſt meeted out.</p>
            <p>And nothing appears more reaſonable, than that the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of a villanous Accuſation, ſhould receive for a Reward of his Merits the Puniſhment due to the Villany; the forgers of a Plot ſhould enjoy as the Fruits of their Labor, what the Plotters ought.</p>
            <p>The Tyrant to whom the Brazen Bull was preſented, thought <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ovid. Triſt</hi> 5 <hi>Eleg.</hi>
               </note> it highly equitable as well as the Poet, that the famous Inventer of this Engine for tormenting of others, ſhould firſt handſel his Work, and try the Experiment, how well it bellow'd.</p>
            <p>Yea, God hath allow'd this procedure, and not only ſo, but <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 21. 24, 25. <hi>Deut.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 18.</note> eſtabliſht it for a ſtandard of Juſtice, Eye for Eye, Tooth for Tooth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and particularly in the preſent Caſe, if he ſhall teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie falſly againſt his Brother, then ſhall ye do unto him, as he thought to do unto his Brother, and by this they proceeded in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Simem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio eſto L.</hi> 12. <hi>Tab. Covarru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vias cap. Peccati, Part.</hi> 2. <hi>Leſſius de Ju. &amp; Juſt. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 33. <hi>dub.</hi> 8. <hi>Grot. de B. &amp; P. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 16. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9. 36.</note> putting the two Elders to death, who had impeached <hi>Suſanna</hi> of Adultery. And according to this Principle it's the common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of Caſuiſts, that a corrupt Judge, a falſe Accuſer, or Evidence ſhould make Satisfaction to the Praty griev'd, propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to the damage he ſuſtain'd by the Sentence, Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Teſtimony.</p>
            <p>And it's correſpondent to his own method of Providence, when he takes the Cauſe into his own hand, by the Juſtice of which it ſo happens, that the Foot of the Wicked is caught and entangled in the ſame Snare, that he laid and privily hid for others, falls in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame Pit he dug. This very Conduct God obſerved in the Sin of <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezebel,</hi> the Dogs lick'd the Blood of the laſt in that very ſpot of Ground, which ſhe by the procuring or ſuborning of falſe Witneſſes robb'd <hi>Naboth</hi> of, together with his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53758:6"/>
Life; and the ſlain Carcaſs of <hi>Ahab,</hi> who coveted an evil Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs againſt his Vineyard, and by it occaſion'd the Perjury and Murther by which this was gain'd, was thrown at <hi>Jehu</hi>'s command into that very portion, who remarqued the Truth of God in the completion of his Prediction, as well as his Juſtice in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. v.</hi> 25. <hi>compare</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. <hi>v.</hi> 23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 36.</note> the affair. So he did in puniſhing <hi>Rudolph</hi> of <hi>Swaben,</hi> the Pſeudo-Emperor, ſet up by Pope <hi>Hildebrand</hi> againſt his lawful Sovereign <hi>Henry</hi> the IV. (which is not only taken notice of by Hiſtorians, but related by them as his own Senſe) whoſe Conſcience being wounded with a Reflection on his guilt, as well as his body was at the Battle of <hi>Elaſtra</hi> or <hi>Eliſter,</hi> having firſt loſt his Right-hand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Godfrey</hi> of <hi>Bulloin</hi> ſtruck him through the Breaſt with the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Abbas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpergens. Sigebert. Gemblac. ad Ann.</hi> 1080.</note> Staff of the Standard he carry'd in that Action, extorted this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion from him, That he juſtly ſuffer'd in that Hand, which he laid upon the Goſpel when he ſwore that Fealty to <hi>Henry</hi> the IV. which he had perfidiouſly broke.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, our Wiſe Neighbor-Nation of <hi>Scotland,</hi> tho I know not whether ſhe exerciſeth this Retaliation againſt falſe Witneſſes (which yet I believe ſhe doth, having great reſpect, in the fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of her Laws, or the practiſe of them to the Imperial) doth it however againſt the Judge; ſo that if at any time, upon the ſcanning o'er again the Judicial Proceedings, it ſhall appear, the Judge, tranſported by Hatred, Envy, or any ſuch vile Paſſion, or ſway'd by Bribes or Intereſt, directed the Jury to bring in a Verdict, which took away wrongfully the impleaded Perſon's Life, he ſhall, if alive at the Re-examination of the affair, ſatisfie for it with his own, or if not, his Eſtate ſhall make Satisfaction proportionate to the Damages the Heirs of the Executed Perſon ſuſtain'd by his Death.</p>
            <p>But foraſmuch as neither making the falſe Deponent ſuffer the Puniſhment enacted againſt the Crime, whatſoever that be, which he injuriouſly objects to the innocent, may be ſufficient to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the Sin of Perjury; nor yet may the infliction of Death, nor the Confiſcation of Eſtate and Goods, together with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual loſs of Liberty in every ſuch Caſe, carry terror enough in them to affright Men, who are audaciouſly wicked from ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturing on it, to execute the Conſpiracy they have entred into againſt the Lives, Fortunes, and good Names of others; becauſe they may hope to cloath themſelves and machinations with ſo much night, to walk in ſuch deep ſilence and thick darkneſs, as not to be deſcry'd by the moſt diligent and piercing Eye, nor the quickeſt Ear, and then if the diveliſh Engine be ſo ſecretly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and the Mine dug ſo deep that they cannot be diſcover'd before hand, the one may be play'd and the other ſprung with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53758:6"/>
diſmal and fatal Succeſs againſt the beſt Men and worthieſt Patriots; it will become the Sageneſs of your Illuſtrious Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, <hi>My Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> to conſider of means, even to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate, if poſſible, the miſchievous deſigns of ſuch, who have a mind to Perjure themſelves to compaſs the ruine of others, upon Confidence they can order matters with ſo much cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and carry them ſo cloſely, as they ſhall not be detected.</p>
            <p>In my Opinion, which I deliver with all deference to your Judgments, it would mightily conduce to this end, if in the ſame Bill you ſhould preſcribe Rules, whereby Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, ſhould regulate themſelves in admitting Perſons to give Teſtimony. For all without diſtinction are not fit to give Teſtimony in many Facts, or to be believ'd; and ſuch who are infamous for Lewdneſs in all the Scenes and Stages of their Life, I take to be very incompetent Witneſſes, and that their Teſtimony, for want of Credibility, ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected.</p>
            <p>It ſeem to me that there is greater Reaſon why the Law ſhould be careful in requiring Qualifications in thoſe, whom <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Articuli ſup Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam</hi> 28 <hi>Edv.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3. 34 <hi>Edv.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 10. 1 <hi>Rich.</hi> 3. 4. <hi>c.</hi>
               </note> ſhe allows to be Witneſſes, as in general that they be Men of unblemiſht fame for their probity, than ſhe is in directing what Choice the Sheriff ſhould make of Jurors, who according to her Ordination is to impanel no ſuſpicious one; but they are to be all of good Fame and Name; ſeeing it is the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of thoſe which wholly influence theſe in their Verdict. Wiſe Nations have conſtituted theſe and theſe Qualifications for Witneſſes, and that thoſe who did not appear ſo condition'd, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nam in Teſtimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is Fides, mores, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitas exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minantur L. in Teſt. ff de Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. In Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibus &amp; vitae quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ſpectari debet &amp; dignitas. L.</hi> 3. §. <hi>lege ff de Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. Grot. de B. &amp; P. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. § 10. <hi>Annot.</hi> 11. <hi>Idem in</hi> 17</note> ſhould not be heard at the Barr.</p>
            <p>According to the <hi>Roman</hi> Law, the Honeſty, the Manners, the Gravity of the Witneſſes were inquired into.</p>
            <p>And the Judges had Conſideration of, and to the Manner and Reputation, and Honor of the Witneſſes lives as the true and ſolid Grounds of Credibility.</p>
            <p>And Servants therefore for the Ignobleneſs of their Condition, and as believing they might for that Reaſon be eaſier cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, were debarr'd from giving Teſtimony, unleſs wrackt to ſpeak the Truth.</p>
            <p>In the Jewiſh Conſtitution, neither Thieves after they had made Reſtitution, nor common Gameſters were lookt upon as any more competent Witneſſes, than Perſons bereſt of their Reaſon. The firſt, I ſuppoſe, they apprehended might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced again to do injuſtice when it ſerv'd their Intereſt, and that the Second, who for lucre were apt to forſwear themſelves at a Gaming-Table, might have the ſame prevailing motive to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53758:7"/>
do it at a Barr, might make no more bones of Cozening by a falſe Oath, than by falſe Play, as he in <hi>Plutarch</hi> averr'd, Men <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plut. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theg.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> were to be cheated by Oaths, as Boys by falſe Dice, or that the former was Mens, the other Childrens play.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Scotland</hi> I am informed the Perſon Arrain'd for Treaſon, hath the liberty to Cite by a Subpoena, [or as they ſpeak, allows Letters of Exculpation] not only Witneſſes of his own Peaceable and Honeſt Converſation, but to confront thoſe, who are Evidence <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mackenz. L. of Scot. B.</hi> 4. <hi>T.</hi> 4.</note> for the Crown, and if they can prove them to be Perſons of a very ill Fame, their Teſtimony ſhall not be accepted againſt the <hi>Priſoner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as ſome ought to be excluded from the Privilege of bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Teſtimony in any caſe, eſpecially Capital ones, for their infamous manner of Living; ſo ſhould Courts be inſtructed or authoriz'd to reject others likewiſe, of whoſe Condition of Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, either by Reaſon of their Obſcurity, or their ſhooting up like Muſhrooms, all on a ſudden, no knowledge can be gain'd. For when this cannot be diſcover'd, the Proſecuted are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of their main guard and principal defence againſt falſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. Upon this reaſon the <hi>Roman</hi> Law wiſely prohibited <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 3. <hi>ff ad Leg. Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel. de Falſari is. Cicero.</hi>
               </note> under ſevere Penalties, the Witneſſes changing their Names, becauſe by this means they would ſo hide themſelves as no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition into or Examination of their Lives can poſſibly be made; as the Cuttle fiſh by the effuſion of a Juice like Ink, ſo blackens the Water that ſhe ſecures her ſelf from being caught by all the Art of the Fiſher-man, and this ſhifting of their Names could not be expounded to be done to any other end, than that they might have the better opportunity to circumvent and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs thoſe they accuſed.</p>
            <p>Had the Law heretofore made theſe the Requiſites of a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs before his Teſtimony could be accepted; a <hi>Fuller</hi> could not have had the impudence or the folly to pretend to be an Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in a Plot, in which he would have involv'd ſome Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Houſe of Commons; nor <hi>Young</hi> and <hi>Blackhed</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in an Accuſation of Treaſon againſt the Archbiſhop of <hi>Cant.</hi> the Bp. of <hi>Roch.</hi> and other Temporal Lords; Nor <hi>L—,K—,W—,</hi>the Preſumption to imagine they ſhould be credited a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>L—ſhire</hi> and <hi>C—ſhire</hi> Gentlemen, by a Jury of the like quality (no more than any conſiering Perſon could have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to think, that Capt. <hi>Wit—</hi>'s diſcovery, that Dr. <hi>Tho—d</hi> and Mr. <hi>Pi—,</hi> had been employ'd by the Lords <hi>Wor—Ayl—</hi>and <hi>Lich—</hi>to tranſact with him, that he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted with a gang of his Fellow-Robbers would kill his Majeſty, as he was Hunting in <hi>Epping</hi> or <hi>Windſor</hi> Foreſt, had any weight of Credibility in it, though he had made it in Confeſſion, or as he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53758:7"/>
was turning off at the Gallows) they being all conſcious to themſelves of the Profligateneſs of their Lives, of having proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted their Reputation, and ſome of them, that they had oftner chang'd their Names, than the dread of Catchpoles had made them change their lurking holes, or their wretched Poverty would permit them to change Shirts.</p>
            <p>And as the Teſtimony of all ſorts of Men without Diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, or any previous inquiry into their Lives upon the meer calling for them by the King's Council ſhould not be admitted; for this is precipitating a Man's Condemnation; ſo neither ſhould the Judges or Gentlemen of the Jury be too eaſie in giving a credulous Ear, or yielding up their Faith, though the Crimes, with which the Priſoner is charg'd, are atteſted by Perſons, who were not of a loſt Fame, if they are of that nature, as would affect their Life, Eſtate, Honor, upon Conviction, unleſs there were concurrent Circumſtances, which render'd their Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion probable. The more enormous the Crime objected againſt the Priſoner, or the more heinous the Puniſhment of it is, the more difficult the Judges and Jurors ſhould be to credit its Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion by a Man of fair and clear Reputation for Honeſty and Integrity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quintillian,</hi> whoſe Art made him capable of in inſtructing <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quintilian l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Difficilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma enim eſt graviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimi cujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſceler is fides.</hi>
               </note> both Bench and Barr, hath mention'd this.</p>
            <p>Beſides, <hi>My Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> it will deſerve your Care, becauſe it may concern your Safety, to get it enacted, that the proof ſhould be ſuch, as ſhould touch not only the Species of the Crime, but reach alſo to the individuality of the Fact, and that likewiſe there ſhould be concurrent Teſtimonies as to the Identcal manner of perpetrating it; two at leaſt, as God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.6.</note> there ſhould be two or three in order to convict any of Rebellion againſt himſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> Idolatry; and as it is practiſed at this day in <hi>Scotland.</hi> For though two ſhould ſwear home againſt a Perſon as to a particular Treaſon, namely, a deſign to Murther a Prince, or ſtir up Inſurrections againſt him, yet a diſcrepancy in their Evidence, as to the intended manner and method of compaſſing his deſign, would afford good ground to ſuſpect the Truth of it.</p>
            <p>He, in whom the Spirit of Wiſdom of the moſt High God was found, proceeded upon this ground, to clear the Innocency of <hi>Suſanna,</hi> after ſhe had been caſt by the point blank and joyntly agreeing Oaths of two Elders, as to the Commiſſion of the Adultery they accuſed her of, and to diſprove their Teſtimony, convicting them of forging a lying Accuſation againſt her, by their differing among themſelves, as to the Place where theſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53758:8"/>
pretended Eye-Witneſſes ſaw the foulneſs acted, the one, when <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Suſan. v.</hi> 25 <hi>&amp; v.</hi> 58.</note> he interrogated them apart, affirming it done under a <hi>Maſtick,</hi> the other under a <hi>Holm-Tree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d the Law thus antecedently directed, it had been impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that C. <hi>Sidney</hi> ſhould have been condemn'd in <hi>Weſt. Hall,</hi> when there was but one ſingle Witneſs, who was poſitive to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy he was accus'd of, ſupported by another, that he ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd a Treaſonable Pamphlet in his Cloſet, which had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proof that it was his own Writing, than one fetch'd from a ſimilitude of Hands. Or that Mr. <hi>Aſh—</hi>ſhould have been Sentenc'd at the <hi>Seſſions-houſe,</hi> for having Papers ſeiz'd upon him (which the Court declar'd to contain Treaſonable Matter) while the Proof, though full and pregnant to that point of Seiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was maim and defective in the making out, even ſo much as by a conformity and compariſon of Hands that he wrote any of them, or by collateral Circumſtances that he knew what they comprehended. The L. <hi>Marl—</hi>could never have been committed for Treaſon upon a ſingle Information, when it could not be reaſonably thought, that he ſhould be either ſo mutable as to engage in a deſign to pluck down that Government, to the raiſing of which he had ſo powerfully contributed, or it ſo ungrateful as to do it againſt that which had careſs'd him with beſtowing Honors upon him, or ſo imprudent as to ſeek to better his Condition by an alteration of it. Nor could the E. of <hi>Hunt—</hi>and other Perſons of Quality have been deny'd the benefit of the Habeas Corpus Bill, when there was but one Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon Oath againſt them: Though <hi>S. A.</hi> had the boldneſs to call a ſingle Teſtimony, the having Evidence againſt each Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, and the art of Equivocating ſo dextrouſly, as to make <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Journal of the Lords Houſe, Nov.</hi> 11. 14, 15. 1692.</note> Witneſſes againſt the Priſoners in his Affidavit, paſs upon the C<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> for a Plurality againſt every ſingle one, and get them thereby remanded to the <hi>Tower.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides the foremention'd Reaſons to bring in ſuch a Bill, you may be encourag'd to do it, from the juſt ground you have to hope that it cannot want the Royal Fiat, <hi>Roy le veult,</hi> to create it an Act as ſoon as tender'd to his Majeſty; He being a Prince of too great Wiſdom, not to underſtand his Intereſt in it, and how beneficial it will be to the Crown; of too great Generoſity to refuſe the People ſo public a good as this will be to them, and of too grateful a Memory, not to oblige you in paſſing it, if you inſiſt upon it, from whoſe Donation, not 6 Years ſince, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the Imperial Crown of this Realm with thanks; of too much Conſtancy to depart from Reſolutions once well taken up by him; and ſince therefore in his Declaration emitted by him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53758:8"/>
when Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> one of the Reaſons aſſign'd for his coming over was to obtain a Reformation of Abuſes committed in the Tryal of Capital Cauſes, and there can be none more foul than Perjury, by which in one breath, the Lives, Eſtates, Honors, of the moſt Noble may be taken away, and they will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in this Danger from Wicked Men, while the Motives to induce them to forſwear themſelves continue more prevalent, than their Fears to ſuffer the ſlight Puniſhment (as it is now) of their Perjury, if that be detected; you cannot apprehend, without an injuſtice, at the ſame time you do ſo, to theſe his He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roic Qualities, that the King of <hi>England</hi> will not redreſs what the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> complain'd of.</p>
            <p>I ſay, you cannot harbour ſuch a Jealouſy without detracting from thoſe his Royal Virtues, and ſuppoſing, He would fly to ſuch little Subterfuges as Captain <hi>Beſſus</hi> did for an Excuſe why he did not fight with thoſe who challeng'd him, that <hi>Beſſus</hi> the Valiant was not bound to anſwer for what <hi>Beſſus</hi> the Coward ſaid or did; or without thinking him (what is not meet) wretchedly careleſs how He tranſmitteh his Great Name to Poſterity, which, in caſe he did not after the gaining of the Diadem, perform what he promis'd before he wore it, might grow into a By-word, as a famous Lawyers did for varying his Judgment with his Place and Station: <hi>The Caſe is alter'd now, quoth</hi> Ployden.</p>
            <p>If then, <hi>My Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> you have any Zeal for God's Honor, as you ſhew'd a great deal in providing againſt the Prophanation of his Holy Day, which yet was but guarding the border and fringe of Religion, for the obſerving of a Day is no more of the Eſſence of honoring him, than Time is of any Civil Action, and if I remember right, againſt the profaning of his Great Name, by cuſtomary Swearing, you ought to ſhew it more, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſollicitous, that it be not treated with inſolent Scorn, as it is by For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearers.</p>
            <p>If you have any regard to the Safety or very Being of your Country, and would divert God's Judgments, which though delay'd for a Seaſon, will at length over-take and puniſh a Nation, where Perjury is ſuffer'd to thrive to the laſt degree, to an utter Exciſion of them.</p>
            <p>If you would not have your Country left Deſolate by Multitudes of its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants tranſporting their Perſons and Effects into Foreign Parts, where their Lives and Eſtates, which here lie expoſed to the Mercy of Perjurious Villains, who have no more regret than Conſcience for the deſtroying both, may be in ſome reaſonable Security.</p>
            <p>If you have any Veneration for its Honor, or would not have it branded abroad with the infamous reproach of being Perfidious, or redeem us from the Scandal of that Imputation, which is caſt upon us, of being a People, who have no Senſe of an Oath.</p>
            <p>If you have any compaſſionate Care for the Lives of your fellow Subjects, which lie continually expoſed to every profligate Raſcal, who hath the Auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs to run the riſque of peeping through an Inch-board, or having his Ears nail'd to it, or at the utmoſt can ſtand the battery of Rotten-Eggs, in caſe he ſhould be deprehended to have ſworn falſly againſt them.</p>
            <p>If you would not have the Land defiled with Innocent Blood, would not have it found in your Skirts, nor Blood touch Blood, nor Robbery com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted with Color of Juſtice, which Crimes drew forth at firſt God's complaint againſt <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and afterwards his ſoareſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon them.</p>
            <p>Or if you have any Tenderneſs for your own dear Lives, or value your own Eſtates and Honors, ſo that you would not by any Circumvention or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53758:9"/>
Supplantation from falſe, mercinary, proſtitute Tongues be deprived of them, to which Danger you lie extremely ſubject, while they are only guarded by ſo ſlender a Penalty, at that of the preſent Law, againſt Lying and Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Lips.</p>
            <p>If you would tranſmit theſe as ſafe to your Poſterities as you receiv'd them from your Anceſters.</p>
            <p>If you would not have your Noble or Generous Blood ſtain'd, your ample or fair Patrimonies annihilated by the Forgery of Crimes againſt you, which confirm'd with falſe Oaths will produce this Calamity.</p>
            <p>If you would have the Crown ſit faſt on the Heads of thoſe Princes on which you have placed it, if you would have them fixt in thoſe Thrones where you have ſeated them; ſince by a falſe Accuſation maintain'd by ſuperadded Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, which, as the Law now ſtands, is little leſs than indemnified, their ableſt Miniſters may be raviſht from them, and be thereby deprived of the Aid and Support of their faithful Counſels. Since the Thrones of Kings are Eſtabliſht <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Proverb.</hi> 12.</note> by Righteouſneſs, and Crown'd Heads ſubſiſt by the Reputation of Juſtice, as well as ordinary Traders, and this Reputation muſt mightily be impair'd, if under their Reigns, the Innocent ſhall want the neceſſary defence of ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Law againſt the Aſſaults of Perjury.</p>
            <p>If you have any regard to the united Wiſhes and Deſires of the beſt and ſobereſt part of the Nation, who conſidering the late Danger, which through the Perjury of Miſcreants loſt to all Virtue and good Name, had encompaſs'd ſome Gentlemen of the firſt Note in their ſeveral Countries, and had like to have ſwallow'd them up, and might probably have ſuckt in many others, had not their wicked Artifices been diſcover'd by a timely Providence, are bent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on requeſting and obtaining ſuch a Security from you; I ſay, if any Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration be had of theſe, you then have, <hi>My Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> all the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to prepare ſuch a Bill, as will procure this Security, which a well built Hope, that it will paſs into a Law, can give you (for you cannot fear that it will miſcarry for want of his Majeſties Signing it, without ſuſpecting him to be leſs gracious than he hath Promis'd or hath Reaſon to be to a People devoted with ſuch Affection to his Service) And all the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Motives, which the Honor of God, the Reputation of your Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive beloved Country; its Safety together with that of his Majeſty, which is deſervedly precious in your Eyes, the private good of each honeſt Man ſingly, and the Public Good of all conjoyntly can ſuggeſt, to incite you to uſe all the Application you poſſibly can, for the diſpacthing of ſo neceſſary and uſeful a Bill, which will make the Nation happy, as far as the covering Innocency, from a Deſtruction at any time deſign'd againſt it can, and your ſelves in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular for ever memorable, by procuring ſo great a Good to it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>WHile theſe Sheets were a Working off, a great Peer I am told, brought into the Houſe of Lords a Bill, worthy of himſelf, his high Station, to the ſame end that this was intended to promote, which I cannot take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, without making all the wiſhes for its Succeſs, which the Juſtice and Honor of it deſerves.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
